Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 9 -- Letters to Franklin 1787-1790 Mss.B.F85inventory09
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 October 10; A.L.S. 3p.; Vaughan, Samuel. St. James's, Jamaica
    Hopes Franklin will live to see the establishment of liberty and the security of property. Writes on behalf of his son Samuel who desires a government office under the new Constitution; thinks a place in the Foreign Department would be most suitable to his talents and inclinations. Obliged to remain in Jamaica another year to look after his property there.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 October 11; A.L.S. 1p.; Broom, Jacob. Wilmington
    Promises to urge Mr. C.J. Killen to pay the money due Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 October 13; L.S. 1p.; Clarkson, Matthew et al. Philadelphia
    Acknowledging the many favors conferred upon them by Franklin; wishing his invaluable life may be long preserved.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 October 15; L.S. 1p.; Pawling, Henry
    Begs Franklin to honor his son and grandson with letters of recommendation to certain gentlemen; their purpose to set out for Kentucky and thence to New Orleans on a trading voyage.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 October 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Hill, Henry. Philadelphia
    Setting forth certain conditions on which he wishes to borrow the sum of £1,000 sterling.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 October 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Redick, David
    Received Franklin's letter by George; promises to carry out his wishes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 October 25; A.L.S. 3p.; Muhlenberg, Gen John Peter Gabriel
    Writes on behalf of Mr. Brencisen, a descendant of a nobel Prussian family who gave up his position in the Prussian army to try his fortune in that of the United States; arrived only to find the war ended; so far has supported his family with difficulty by keeping a small school in the country; being now deprived of this position, desires to return to his own country. Busily engaged in the Board of Property.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 October 31; A.L.S. 5p.; Sargent, Winthrop, 1753-1820
    Transmits his observations on the weather for the months of September and October. Has been informed that the Academy of Manheim has been attentive in composing correspondent instruments for almost all meterological observations, some of which they are desirous of depositing in the various climes of this and other countries for comparative observations; shall be pleased to take charge of a set if that is the case.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 November 3; L. in 3d P. 2p.; Wells, Richard. Philadelphia
    Theophilus Gardner, for want of funds, is unable to claim an estate in Jamaica belonging, to his family; begs Franklin to read the enclosed papers and see Mr. Gardner for a few minutes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 November 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Elam, Joseph. Philadelphia
    Enclosing a copy of his letter to Gov. [Edmund] Randolph, protesting against being thought insane, and asking protection against being returned to the Pennsylvania Hospital as an escapted patient [4 p.]. Desires to meet his accusers face to face in Franklin's presence; if they will not agree to this, wishes his case laid before the Pennsylvania Assembly, in order that he may quietly enjoy the liberty of a freeholder and citizen.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 November 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Partridge, Elizabeth. Boston
    Reminds him of his promise to settle in Boston; news of the Mecoms and Miss Betsy Steel; death of Mr. Benjamin Kent. Desires a copy of the letter he wrote when he continued the post-office to her mother. Enclosing a letter [2 p.] from Anne Hey to her father, Dr. Philip Van Horn, acknowledging the justice of his opposition to her marriage, detailing her husband's cruelty and desertion, her inability to support her two babies, and her wish to be forgiven and taken home again; begs Franklin to use his influence with Dr. Van Horn [in Philadelphia].
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 November 29; A.L.S. 3p.; Small, Alexander. Worcester England
    Account of a remedy (caustic volatilc alkali) which he and others have found very efficacious in cases of stone. Gave Franklin's remarks on Ventilation to the Royal Society of Edinburgh; could not find it in the American Philosophical [Society's] Transactions.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 December 7; A.L.S. 1p.; Childs, Francis
    Expects to leave for Albany to attend the present session of the Legislature; on his return will proceed immediately to Philadelphia in order to make a final settlement of their account. Has ordered for Franklin a copy of his Sketch of the Debates of their Convention.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 December 13; A.L.S. 4p.; Vaughan, Samuel Jr. Port-au-Prince, St. Domingo
    Superiority of the mountain rice cultivated in St. Domingo. Numerous East Indian plants which flourish in the West Indies; too cold for the tea plant; hopes that will thrive better in the States. Hurricanes on the islands; those convered with woods are immune; whereas the prevalence of them in Jamaica followed rapidly on the clearing away of the mountain woods.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 December 15; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Haygarth, Dr. John. Chester, England
    Sending the enclosed papers; if they meet with Franklin's approval, begs he will communicate them to his countrymen in whatever manner he deems best. A few years before sent him, by Dr. [Thomas] Percival, as Inquiry how to prevent the Small-pox.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1788 December 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Webster, Pelatiah. Philadelphia
    The Society for Political Inquiries having advertised a premium for the best system of taxation, offers the enclosed essay.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 January; A.L.S. 3p.; Price, Richard, 1723-1791
    Death of [Jonathan Shipley,] Bishop of St. Asaph. Messages to Dr. [Benjamin] Rush. Rejoiced at the adoption of the new Federal Constitution. Affairs in England; the King's insanity. Death of Lord Grantley.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, X, 380; Bigelow, X, 42).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778?] Monday; A.L.S. 1p.; Coxe, Tench
    Concerning the determination of the Abolition Society to forward several letters for the Governors of the other States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L.S. 3p.; Thomas, -----
    With reference to his claim against Bache and Shee, of Philadelphia, and Mr. [Jonathan] Williams [Jr.], of Nantes, for a bale of dry goods shipped through the latter and for which he has not received a settlement.
    (In French. Press copy.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1788]; A.L.S. 2p.; Tobine, K James. Philadelphia
    Excellent progress made by Franklin's school; unable to board and clothe himself on his present salary; his plan to live in the school-house; obliged to ask Franklin to advance him a quarter's salary.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778]; A.L.S. 2p.; A.L.S. 3p.; Tobine, James K
    Request Dr. Franklin to head a subscription to enable him to publish his poem.
    Also a request for an increase in his salary as teacher in the Charity School.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1788.] Saturday morning.; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Warville, Jean Pierre Brissot de
    Sending a volume entitled " Mémoires de l'Académie" which he has just received.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 January 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Long, Elizabeth. Philadelphia
    Applies to him as the father of Pennsylvania for aid on behalf of herself and four small children.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 January 21; A.L.S. 2p.; Maschal, ----- Sr. Chambery
    Desires information concerning the practicability of establishing in America a manufactory for all sorts of hats.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 January 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Marchand, Madame. Paris
    Money due her by M. de Charme, who went to Philadelphia to avoid his engagements in Paris; by Franklin's advice put her affairs in Mr. [Thomas] Barclay's hands; has heard nothing; begs him to speak to Mr. Barclay.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 January 29; A.L.S. 2p.; Arthaud, Charles. Au Cap François
    Have elected Mr. Samuel Vaughan a member of their Society, Le Circle des Philadelphes; sends by him two tokens from the Society, one for Franklin and the other for the [American] Philosophical Society.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 February 9; A.L.S. 4p.; Barry, Amelia. Leghorn
    The little means left by Mr. Barry is in leases; in four years she will have no resources; desires to bury herself in the Apennines; her eldest daughter turned Roman Catholic. Begs Franklin to secure to her children the city lot left by him in the hands of Mr. Israel Pemberton. Acknowledging his kindness in the affair of the maps; fancies Gov. [Thomas] Pownall never succeeded in getting the balance of the account from Mr. [John] Almon.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 February 16; A.L.S. 1p.; Holmes, Abiel. Midway, Georgia
    Desiring Franklin to furnish him with a list of books suitabled for a general (private) library; purposes to make a collection of about four hundred volumes; although divinity is his chief study, will aim to pay attention to literature in general.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 February 20; A.L.S. 3p.; Bon de Corcelles, Pierre. Neufchâtel
    Unable to emigrate to America; sends him the printed announcements of his memoir on American liberty.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 Febraury 21; A.L.S. 4p.; Le Veillard. Louis Guillaume. Passy
    Desires to be useful to Mr. Gouverncur Morris; expects to dine with Mr. Morris at the Duchesse d'Enville's; hopes to see a great deal of him. News of Franklin from M. Saugrain [de Vigny]. Presses him about his memoirs. Affairs in France; States-General convoked for April 27th. Franklin's work on the "difficulty of establishing a good Constritution founded entirely on the Sacred Writings" delighted him much; translated and printed in Paris. Bitterly cold winter; great misery among the people; commends the use of potatoes among the poor. Will take the music to Mme. Brillon, the first interpreter in France of American productions of this sort.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 February 22; A.L. 2p.; La Rochefoucauld, Duc de
    Franklin's retirement to the country after his public office is terminated; hopes he will find time then to finish his memoirs. Need in France of a head like Franklin's. Pleasure he derived from his brief acquaintance with Mr. [Gouverneur] Morris.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 February 24; A.L.S 2p.; Newenham, Sir Edward. Dublin
    Sending a paper with the important debates on the Viceroy's insolent answer to both houses of Parliament; censure passed by them on the Viceroy; all Ireland on their side; hopes for certain reforms.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 February 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Vaughan, William. London
    Happy to hear that he is able to continue the history of his own life. Sends him Chambers's Dictionary of Arts and Sciences; knows of no better English Encyclopaedia. Glad to see that the prejudices and habits arising from the war, have given place to industry and sobriety. Revolutions in Europe all tending to a general improvement in manners and wiser systems.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 February 28; A.L.S. 2p.; Grand, Ferdinand
    Convalescent from a serious illness. Sends him Le Voyage de Grèce by L'Abbé [Jean Jacques] Barthélemy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 March 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Sr
    Fate of the books which Franklin sent him to sell.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 March 6; A.L. 4p.; Brillon, Mme
    Hopeful outlook for America. Crisis in the life of France; begs Franklin to pray for her country. His plan to retire to the country; her own joy in a primitive life. Messages to his grandson. News of her own family.
    Printed in Putnam's Monthly, Jan., 1907, 436.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 March 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Moustier, comte de
    Removal of the packet boats between France and America renders correspondence much more difficult. Delay in the meeting of the new Congress likely to have a bad effect on public opinion; hopes the wisdom of their future measures will efface this first impression; high hopes of a close union of France and America under the new Administration.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 March 16; A.L.S. 2p.; Barton, William. Philadelphia
    Understands that four Trustees of the College [of Philadelphia] are to be elected that day; desires, with Franklin's approval, to have his name proposed for one of them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 March 29; A.L.S. 2p.; St. Olympe, -----, chevalier de. Port-au-Prince
    Introducing M. [François Louis] Suleau.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 March 31; A.L.S. 1p.; Vaughan, Samuel Jr. New York
    Sending [Jacques] Necker's speech to the Notables; if America does not make haste, other nations will become examples for her. Looks forward to seeing Franklin soon; three members lacking to complete both Houses. [of Congress].
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 April 17; A.L.S. 2p.; Gramaguac, -----
    On the part of the Society of Friends of the Blacks, sends him copies of various discourses and letters, with a list of the Society's members; M. Brissot de Warville, the soul of the Society; he will probably be appointed to present to the States-General a memoir, requeting them to name a Committee to examine the question of abolition; promises to keep him informed of the Society's work.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 April 23; A.L.S. 3p.; Small, Alexander. Worcester England
    Hopes America will guard against one great evil, a provision for the poor; poor rates in England said to exceed three millions. Received the apologue; sorry to see that England's treatment of America still rankles; England's large debt and worse extravagance; her commercial advantages. France abundantly punished for her treachery to England. Compares Franklin to Timoleon; deserves a Plutarch to hand him down to posterity. Base manner in which [Francis] Bacon has been painted; few historians able to blend the philosopher and politician. Has withdrawn Franklin's paper on Ventilation from the Society of Edinburgh; their criticism of it was that it contained nothing new. Messages to Mrs. [Mary] Hewson and family. Desires to know how Mr. [John] Penn stands as to property; base abuse of Philadelphia's noble [High] street by placing a market in it.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 April 25; A.L. 7p.; Le Veillard, Louis Guillaume
    State of affairs in France; on the eve of assembling the States-General; freedom of the press; demands for a Constitution; the nobility's insistence upon voting by orders; fears this will cause a schism; the Duke of Orleans a prominent figure. Great disorders among the laboring classes. Grand Mass performed at which the entire Court was present. Opening of the States-General; speeches made. Daily journal of the Convention suppreseed after two numbers had appeared. Claims of the nobility the first difficulty. Names of some of the deputies chosen.
    Printed, in part, in Works (Sparks, X, 387).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 April 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Bard, John. New York
    Introducing his granddaughter; illness of his wife.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 May 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Barton, William. Philadelphia
    Arrival of Mr. Aspinwall from Connecticut, with the laudable purpose of promoting the culture of silk; fears his project will fall through with out the patronage of two or three gentlemen of distinction; Franklin's name would be of great service to him; reasons why he should be encouraged.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 May 4; A.L.S. Tho[ma]s Willing. 1p.; The Bank of North America. Philadelphia
    Concerning the renewal of a small note.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 May 13; A.L.S. 2p.; Harris, Robert. New York
    Was First Lieutenant on board the "Reprisal" which had the honor to carry Franklin to France; begs a line of recommendation to President Washington or Vice-President Adams; wishes a position which would enable him to provide for his family; having only one arm, is unable to earn his bread by hard labor at sea.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 May 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Webster, Noah Jr. Hartford
    Enclosing a letter from Abiel Holmes, whom he begs leave to introduce to Franklin. Has finished his Dissertations on the Language; will send Franklin a copy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 May 25; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Kinsey, Philip
    Informs him that his brother James, about 30 years ago, lent him a mahogany box containing sundry geometrical solid bodies, being the first six books of Euclid's elements, which were never returned. If the box can be obtained in good order, he can dispose of it for as much as it cost him; or if he would like to keep them, he can have the other box containing the remaining six books.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 May 26; A.L.S. 1p.; Vaughan, John
    Mr. Russell about to sail for England; expects to see Dr. [Joseph] Priestley and will take charge of anything for him or any other of Franklin's friends.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 May 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Small, Alexander. London
    Sending Franklin the papers on Ventilation; hopes he will amend and correct whatever is amiss.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 June 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Small, Alexander. London
    Has used Franklin's suggestion to erect his ear into a kind of trumpet when he wishes to hear anyhthing; finds it a help. His experiments with bees, and with the insects which destroy hops; explanation of the origin of insects as he conceived it occurred.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 June 9; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Ruston, Dr. Thomas. Philadelphia
    Acknowledging his very obliging certificate.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 June 12; A.L.S. 3p.; Fleming, Joseph. Philadelphia
    Acknowledging Franklin's former kindness to his aged father in England; applies for further assistance for the old man; his heart full of filial feeling but he is unable to assist him financially.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 June 14; A.L.S. 4p.; König, August. Philadelphia
    Account of his emigration from Hanover, of a shipwreck, the loss of all his belongings and his arrival with his family at Charleston, naked, sick and poor; aid given them by charitable persons; their arrival in Philadelphia; desires to pay his respects to Franklin and to become an American citizen.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 June 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Broom, Jacob. Wilmington
    Concerning payment by Chief-Justice Killen of a debt due Franklin, by his son Jacob A. Killen; cause of delay due to Mr. Killen's not having received any of his salary for three years; prospect of its being paid after harvest.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 June 17; A.L.S. 4p.; Steinsky, François. Prague
    Three years before, sent him a translation of his (Franklin's) works in German together with the Proceedings of a Society under the auspices of the Prince de Fürstenberg. Sends him now his own small periodical work as well as a work on physics by Abbé Gruber. Question of publishing a sketch of Franklin's life with a list of his writings.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 June 17; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Bond, Phineas Jr. Philadelphia
    Sending Franklin some English papers.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 June 18; A.L.S. 3p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Satisfaction in France over the state of affairs in America. Present motions in the House of Representatives for raising a revenue likely to decrease imports; work on this subject by M. Le Trone ( De l'Administration Provincial et de la Reform de l'Impot ). Forwards the Proceedings of the States-General; cloquent and crudite debates on political questions.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 June 21; A.L.S. 3p.; Desnos, Odolant. Alençon
    Begs Franklin to insert a notice in the principal American newspapers, asking for any information of his son, Gaspard Jacques Desnos Odolant, who sailed for America in June, 1777, and has never been heard from since.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 June 22; A.L.S. 3p.; Lovely, Jno
    Begging Franklin's influence with the [Supreme] Executive Council [of Pennsylvania] to obtain his release.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 June 29; A.L.S. 2p.; Morris, Robert. New York
    Sure that Franklin's bills were honored by M. [Ferdinand] Grand, but has no advices respecting the time of acceptance or payment. Last advices received from Mr. G[ouverneur] Morris at Paris; hears he is much in fashion there.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 June 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Begouan, Demeaux and Co. Havre
    Sending Franklin a packet confided to them by M. [Ferdinand] Grand of Paris.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 June; A.L.S. 2p.; Howland, Samuel. Newport, R.I
    Desires to peruse two volumes, entitled The Preceptor, Treating of the Polite Branches of Literature; understands that Franklin gave them to Sylvester Folger, whose widow now owns them, but is unwilling to loan them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 July 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Vaughan, John
    Settlement of a small money matter. News of his family in England. Costly illuminations in London in honor of the King's recovery; unpopularity of the Prince [of Wales.]
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 July 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Thomas. Philadelphia
    Concerning the interest due on a certain bond; hopes to pay it on the sixth.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 July 1; L. in 3d P. 1p.; La Terriere, -----. Bordentown
    Desiring the return of a volume of M. [Jacques] Necker's writings lent to Franklin five or six months ago.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 July 14; A.L.S. 5p.; Hare, Robert. Philadelphia
    Trusts Franklin's papers will promote a reformation in the past system of education; discusses his plan to separate the English school from the jurisdiction of the Provost and Faculty of the College [of Philadelphia]; thinks this too radical at present.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 July 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    French politics; the first two orders forced to unite with the Third Estate; the West Indies represented in the National Assembly, a good precedent for other European States holding Colonies.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 July 18; A.L.S. 2p.; Vaughan, Samuel Jr. Philadelphia
    Sum charged for the musical bells he brought Franklin from Europe. List of books lent to Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 July 18; A.L.S. 2p.; Walter, John. London
    Sending him a number of books for which he subscribed; his failure to procure the King's name at the head of his list of subscribers. due, he thinks, to Franklin's name being there. Difficulties in the way of his completing his system of logographic printing; begs Franklin to recommend him both as printer and bookseller.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 July 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Mather, Samuel. London
    Sending him an essay on the Powers and Mechanism of Nature, by his friend Robert Young, Esq., also the first report of the London Philanthropic Society, of which Mr. Young was the institutor; recommends Mr. Young for membership in the [American] Philosophical Society.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 July 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Nelson, William Jr. Williamsburg
    Reminding Franklin that Mr. John Paradise never became a British subject but took the oath of fidelity to the United States when Franklin was Ambassador to France; desires a certificate of his having taken the oath, in order to settle a law-suit.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 July 21; A.L.S. 3p.; König, August. Philadelphia
    Reminding Franklin of his impoverished state; received promise of aid from Governor [Thomas] Mifflin provided he could procure a recommendation from Franklin; hopes he will not refuse him this grace.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1789 July 22; A.L.S. 2p.; Le Veillard, Louis Guillaume